<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sayings of women, which were spoken upon sundry occasions, in several places of the Scriptures. / Briefly collected and set together ...</title>
            <author>Bathurst, Elizabeth, d. 1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B17539</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">48187608</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207855</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248523303</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1135B</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">48187608</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B17539)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207855)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2184:14c)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sayings of women, which were spoken upon sundry occasions, in several places of the Scriptures. / Briefly collected and set together ...</title>
                  <author>Bathurst, Elizabeth, d. 1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Andrew Sowle at the Crooked-Billet in Holloway-Lane in Shoreditch,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Elizabeth Bathurst.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
                  <note>With: Truth vindicated. / By ... Elizabeth Bathurst ... [London] : Printed for T. Sowles ..., 1691 -- Truth's vindication, A gentle stroke to wipe off the foul aspersions, false accusations and misrepresentations cast upon the people of God call'd Quakers. London : Printed and sold by Andrew Sowle ..., 1683.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Women in the Bible --  Quotations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207855:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207855:1"/>
            <p>THE SAYINGS OF Women, Which were spoken upon sundry occrsions, in several places of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Briefly Collected and set together to shew how the Lord <hi>poured out of his Spirit upon the whole House of Israel;</hi> not only on the Male; but also on the Female; and made them <hi>Stewards of the manifold Gifts of his Grace;</hi> and as those who knew they must give an account of their Stewardship to the Lord.</p>
            <p>So did all the Women that were wise in Heart, manage their particular Talents, to the Praise and Glory of God.</p>
            <p>Printed and Sold by <hi>Andrew Sowle</hi> at the Crooked-Billet in <hi>Holloway-Lane</hi> in <hi>Shoreditch,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:207855:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:207855:2"/>
            <head>The SAYINGS of Women, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> WE find the Sayings of faithful <hi>Sarah,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Son <hi>Isaac,</hi> the Child of Promise, (to whom the Inheritance belonged) when she saw <hi>Ishmael</hi> mocking of him, she said to <hi>Abraham</hi> her Husband, <hi>Cast out this Bond-woman and her Son, for the Son of this Bond-woman shall not be Heir with my Son, even with</hi> Isaac. And God commended her Care, and justified her Speech, saying, unto <hi>Abraham, Let it not be grievous in thy sight, because of the Lad, and because of the Bond-woman; in all that</hi> Sarah <hi>hath said unto thee, hearken unto her Voice, for in</hi> Isaac <hi>shall thy Seed be called,</hi> Gen. 21.10.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, We find <hi>Rebecca,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Isaac,</hi> speaking to the Lord, and the Lord answering her, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.22, 23. when she was with Child of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Esau;</hi> the Children strugling together within her, she went to inquire of the Lord [not of Doctors] saying, <hi>If it be so, why am I thus?</hi> And the Lord said
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:207855:3"/> unto her, <hi>Two Nations are in thy Womb, and two manner of People shall be separated from thy Bowels; and the one People shall be stronger than the other People, and the Elder shall serve the Younger.</hi> And after the Children were Born and come to Age, she spoke unto her Son <hi>Jacob,</hi> and instructed him how he should obtain the Blessing, which God had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.6. and so on. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards she took care of her Son <hi>Jacob,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Marriage, saying to <hi>Isaac</hi> her Husband, <hi>If</hi> Jacob <hi>take a Wife of the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of</hi> Heath, <hi>such as these, which are of the Daughters of the Land, what good shall my Life do me?</hi> Vers the last. And <hi>Isaac</hi> approved of her Speech, and called <hi>Jacob</hi> and blessed him, and said unto him, <hi>Thou shalt not take a Wife of the Daughters of</hi> Canaan, Chap. 28.1.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, We find <hi>Rachel</hi> and <hi>Leah</hi> speaking unto <hi>Jacob</hi> in these wholsom Words, saying, <hi>Now therefore whatsoever God hath said unto thee, do,</hi> Gen. 31.10.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, We find <hi>Miriam</hi> the Prophetess speaking to an Assembly of Women, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.20.21. when <hi>Moses</hi> had made an end of his Song of Praises to the Lord, for the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Deliverance of his People; then <hi>Miriam</hi> the Prophetess,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 68.25.</note> the Sister of <hi>Aaron,</hi> took a <hi>Timbrell</hi> in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:207855:3"/> her Hand, and all the Women went out after her with Timbrels and with Dances; and <hi>Miriam</hi> answered them, and said, <hi>Sing ye to the Lord, for he hath triumphed gloriously; the Horse and his Rider hath he thrown into the Sea,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, We find <hi>Deborah,</hi> a valiant Mother and Judge in <hi>Israel,</hi> (and she was also a Prophetess) speaking to <hi>Barack</hi> a Captain, who had ten Thousand men at his Feet, yet she instructed him how he should go up against <hi>Sessera,</hi> (Captain of <hi>Jabins</hi> Army, the Children of <hi>Israels</hi> Enemy) and she said, <hi>I will surely go up with thee, notwithstanding the Battel thou takest shall not be for thine Honour, for the Lord shall sell</hi> Sissera <hi>into the Hands of a Woman;</hi> Read <hi>Judges</hi> 4. throughout. And then we have her Song, wherein she magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Name of the Lord, and said, <hi>Blessed be</hi> Jael <hi>above Women, the Wife of</hi> Heber; <hi>blessed shall she be in the Tent,</hi> &amp;c. Judg. 5.24. And she made a large Declaration of the Righteous Acts of the Lord, in the sore go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and following Verses; for he it was that had avenged his People of their Enemies.</p>
            <p n="6">6thly, We find <hi>Jeptha's</hi> Daughter, saying to her Father, <hi>As thou hast opened thy Mouth unto the Lord, so do unto me according to what hath proceeded out of thy Mouth, forasmuch as the Lord hath taken Vengeance for thee on thine
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:207855:4"/> Enemies, even of the Children of</hi> Amon, Judg. 11.26.</p>
            <p n="7">7thly, We find <hi>Manoah's</hi> Wife saying to her Husband, <hi>A man of God came unto me, and his Countenance was like the Countenance of an Angel of God, very terrible; but I asked him not whence he was, neither told he me his Name; but he said unto me, Behold thou shalt conceive and bear a Son; and now drink no Wine, nor strong Drink, neither eat any unclean thing, for the Child shall be a</hi> Nazarite <hi>to God from the Womb, to the day of his Death,</hi> Judg. 13.7. And when <hi>Manoah</hi> said to his Wife, <hi>We shall surely dye, because we have seen God;</hi> his Wife being more stedfast in Faith, wisely answered and encouraged him, saying, <hi>If the Lord were pleased to kill us, he would not have received Burnt-Offering and a Meat-offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at our Hands; neither would he have shewed us all these things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8thly, We find <hi>Naomy</hi> speaking concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her own Adversity, saying to the People of <hi>Bethlehem; Call me not</hi> Naomy, <hi>call me</hi> Marah, <hi>for the Almighty hath dealt bitterly with me; I went out full, and the Lord hath brought me home again empty, and hath afflicted me,</hi> Ruth. 1, 20, 21.</p>
            <p n="9">9thly, We find <hi>Ruth,</hi> the <hi>Moabitis,</hi> speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing comfortably to <hi>Naomy</hi> her Mother, in her sorrow, saying, <hi>Intreat me not to leave
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207855:4"/> thee, nor to return from following thee; for whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou goest, I will go, and where thou lodgest I will lodge; thy People shall be my People; &amp; thy God my God; where thou dyest, will I dye, and there will I be buried; The Lord do so to me, and more also, if ought but Death part thee and me,</hi> Ruth 1.16, 17. And afterwards, both these Women found Favour from the Lord; and the Women of the City blessed the Lord on their behalf, <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.14.</p>
            <p n="10">10thly, We find <hi>Hannah</hi> praying in the Temple, and pouring out her Soul before the Lord; and the Lord heard her, and granted her Petition, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. from <hi>Vers.</hi> 10. to 18. And when her request was grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, she made a fervent and large Speech, in magnifying and exalting the Lord, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. from <hi>Vers.</hi> 1. to 10.</p>
            <p n="11">11thly, We find when <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> had made a great slaughter upon the <hi>Philistines,</hi> the Women came out of all the Cities of <hi>Israel,</hi> Singing and Dancing, with Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Musick; <hi>And the Women answered one another as they plaid, and said,</hi> Saul <hi>hath slain his Thousands, and</hi> David <hi>his ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands,</hi> 1 Sam. 18.6, 7. And as the Women were pertakers of outward Salvation and Deliverance, as well as the Men, by <hi>David</hi> in the time of the Law; so are they pertakers with their Brethren of inward Salvation and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:207855:5"/> Deliverance from the Devil, by Christ, the Captain of our Salvation: And therefore they ought to Praise and make Melody in their Hearts to the Lord, now in the time of the Gospel.</p>
            <p n="12">12thly, We find <hi>Abigal,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Nabal,</hi> speaking to King <hi>David,</hi> saying, <hi>Let thine Hand-maid, I pray thee, speak in thine Audience, and hear the Words of thine Hand-maid.</hi> And so she went on, and preach't a large Sermon to him, as we find written, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31. And <hi>David</hi> the King heard her patiently, and afterwards he said unto her, <hi>Blessed be the Lord God of</hi> Israel <hi>which sent thee this day to meet me; and blessed be thy Advice, and blessed be thou, which hast kept me this day from coming to shed Blood,</hi> Vers. 32, 33. So we see this Wise Woman, by her Prudence and Innocence, saved her House from De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</p>
            <p n="13">13thly, We find the Woman of <hi>Tekoah</hi> speaking to King <hi>David;</hi> yea, she commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him, till she convinced him of the Matter she had to say unto him, see 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.4. and so on. Though she spoke in a Parable, yet by her discretion she made Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Absalom,</hi> and caused the King to call home again his Banished, which he had expelled from him.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:207855:5"/>14thly, We find a <hi>Wise Woman</hi> of the City of <hi>Abel,</hi> speaking to <hi>Joab</hi> the General, yea, she preached to him, and told him, <hi>She was one of them that were faithful in</hi> Israel, <hi>and thou seekest to destroy a City and Mother in</hi> Israel; (said she) <hi>Why wilt thou swallow up the Inheritance of the Lord?</hi> 2 Sam. 20. from Vers. 16. to 20. So she convinced him, and preserved the City: And her Wisdom, Courage and Faith is recorded to Poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p n="15">15thly, We find a poor Widdow speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> saying, <hi>I have but a handful of Meal in a Barrel, and a little Oyl in a Cruse, and behold I am gathering two Sticks that I may go in and dress it for me and my Son, that we may eat it and dye,</hi> 1 Kings 17.12. Yet in Faith she made the Prophet a Cake thereof first; and she found that her Meal and Oyl wasted not, as you read <hi>Vers.</hi> 16. for the Lord gave in a supply, who had commanded her to sustain the Prophet, <hi>Vers.</hi> 9. So she had the reward both of her Faith &amp; Works.</p>
            <p n="16">16thly, We find the <hi>Shunamite</hi>-Woman speaking to her Husband concerning the Prophet <hi>Elisha,</hi> saying, <hi>Behold! now I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that this is a Holy Man of God, which passeth by us continually: Let us make a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I pray thee, on the Wall, and set for him there a Bed, and a Table, and a Stool, and a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207855:6"/> Candle-stick, and it shall be when he cometh to us, that he shall turn in thither,</hi> 2 Kings 4.9, 10. Thus she was sensible of the necessity of the Prophet in his Journey; and according to her care, the Prophet was careful it might be recompenced to her; see Vers. 13. For she was a great Woman, and had no Child, therefore the Prophet told her, <hi>She should have a Son,</hi> and she had so, according to his word: And when the Child dyed, she had Faith to believe (and also told her Husband) <hi>That if she went to the man of God, all should be well:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.35.</note> And it was so, for by Faith she received her Dead raised to Life again, as you may read, Vers. 23. and 36.</p>
            <p n="17">17thly, We find a captive Maid, who was brought out of the Land of <hi>Israel,</hi> and waited upon the Wife of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syrian,</hi> (who was a Leper) saying to her Mistriss, <hi>Would God, my Lord were with the Prophet that is in</hi> Samaria, <hi>for he would reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him of his Leprosie.</hi> Thus she spoke from the sense she had of the Power of the Lord, which he would shew through his Prophet; and it proved so, for <hi>Naaman</hi> went unto him, and was healed, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.23.</p>
            <p n="18">18thly, We find <hi>Huldah</hi> the Prophetess, which dwelt in the Colledge in <hi>Jer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>salem,</hi> speaking to <hi>Hilkiah</hi> the Priest, and <hi>Shaphan</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:207855:6"/> the Scribe, and to the King's Chancellor, which he sent, and commanded to commune with her, and to them, and those that came with them, she made a large declaration in the Name of the Lord, as you may read, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. from <hi>vers.</hi> 12. to the end. Now here, neither King nor Priest, despised a Woman's Speech.</p>
            <p n="19">19thly, We find Queen <hi>Esther</hi> speaking to King <hi>Ahasuerus,</hi> in behalf of the poor <hi>Jews</hi> her People, <hi>Mordica</hi> her Uncle having sent unto her, she bid the Messengers return him this answer, <hi>Gather together all the</hi> Jews <hi>that are present in</hi> Shushan, <hi>and fast ye for me; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eat nor drink three Days, Night nor Day; I and my Maidens will fast likewise: And</hi> (with Courage and Resolution she said) <hi>so will I go in unto the King, which is not according to the Law, and if I perish, I perish,</hi> Esth. 4.16. And by her discreet Behaviour, she obtained favour of the King, (God inclining his Heart) so that he held out the Golden Scepter to her, and said unto her, <hi>What wilt thou Queen</hi> Esther, <hi>and what is thy Request? it shall be given thee to the half of the Kingdom,</hi> Chap. 5.2, 3. So again, Chap. 7.2. <hi>Then</hi> Esther <hi>the Queen answer'd, and said, If I have found favour in thy sight, O King! and if it please the King, let my Life be given me at my Petition, and my People at my Request; For
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207855:7"/> we are sold, I and my People to be destroyed, to be slain, and to perish: Bat if we had been sold for Bond-men and Bond-women, I had held my Tongue, although the Enemy cannot countervail the King's damage. Then King</hi> Ahasuerus <hi>answered, and said unto</hi> Esther <hi>the Queen, Who is he? and where is he that durst presume in his Heart to do so? And</hi> Esther <hi>said, The Adversary and Enemy is this wicked</hi> Haman, Vers. 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>And</hi> Esther <hi>spake yet again before the King, and fell down at his Feet, and besought him with Tears, to put away the Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of</hi> Haman, <hi>and his Device that he had devised against the</hi> Jews. <hi>Then the King held out the golden Scepter toward</hi> Esther; <hi>so</hi> Est<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her <hi>arose, and stood before the King, and said, If it please the King, and if I have found favour in his sight, and the thing seem right before the King, and if it be pleasing in his Eyes, let it be written to reverse the Letter devised hy</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>which he wrote to destroy the</hi> Jews, <hi>which are all in the King's Provinces; For how can I endure to see the Evil that shall come upon my People? Or how can I endure to see the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of my Kindred?</hi> Chap. 8.3, 4, 5, 6. And the King granted it. So by her Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Faith, and innocent Resolution, she saved her People, and became a Nursing-Mother in <hi>Israel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20thly, We find <hi>Zeresh,</hi> the Wife of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207855:7"/>
               <hi>Haman,</hi> saying to her Husband (before the Queen had made complaint against <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) If</hi> Mordica <hi>be of the Seed of the</hi> Jews, <hi>before whom thou hast begun to fall, thou shalt not prevail against him, but shalt surely fall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,</hi> Esth. 6.13.</p>
            <p n="21">21thly, We find King <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Mother saying to her Son, by way of Instruction; <hi>Give not thy Strength unto Women, nor thy Ways to that which destroyeth Kings. It is not for Kings, O</hi> Lemuel, <hi>it is not for Kings to drink Wine, nor for Princes, strong Drink; lest they forget the Law, and pervert the Judgment of any of the Afflicted: Give strong Drink unto him that is ready to perish, and Wine to those that be of heavy Hearts: Let him drink and forget his Poverty, and remember his Misery no more: Open thy Mouth for the Dumb in the cause of all such as are appointed to Destruction: Judge Righteously, and plead the Cause of the Poor and Needy,</hi> Prov. 31. from Vers. 3. to 9.</p>
            <p>Thus we find many renowned Women recorded in the Old Testament, who had received a Talent of Wisdom and Spiritual Understanding from the Lord; as good Stewards thereof they improv'd &amp; imploy'd the same to the Praise and Glory of God.</p>
            <p>So likewise in the <hi>New-Testament</hi> we find another Number of many Daughters,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207855:8"/> who as they were made Heirs of the Grace of Life, together with their Brethren; so upon sundry occasions they spoke and praised the Lord, who had bestowed Mercy on them.</p>
            <p>And here, <hi>First;</hi> We find the Woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> speaking unto Christ in behalf of her Daughter, crying out, and saying, <hi>Have Mercy on me, O Lord, thou Son of</hi> David; <hi>my Daughter is grievously vexed with a Devil,</hi> Mat. 15.22. And again, she came and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped him, saying, <hi>Lord help me,</hi> Vers. 25. But he answered her, <hi>It is not meet to take the Childrens Bread, and cast it unto Dogs.</hi> And she said, <hi>Truth Lord, yet the Dogs eat of the Crumbs which fall from their Masters Table.</hi> Then Jesus answered, and said unto her, <hi>O Woman! great is thy Faith; be it unto thee even as thou wilt: And her Daughter was made whole from that very Hour,</hi> Vers. 27, 28.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, We find a Worthy and noble Act recorded of a Woman, who having an Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaster-Box of very precious Ointment; 'tis said, <hi>She poured it on Jesus his Head, as he sate at Meat,</hi> Mat. 26.7. For which the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples reproved her; but when Jesus under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood it, he spoke in her Justification, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them, <hi>Why trouble ye the Woman,</hi> &amp;c? <hi>Verily I say unto you, wheresoever this Gospel shall be preached throughout the whole World, there
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:207855:8"/> shall also this, that this Woman hath done, be told for a Memorial of her;</hi> as you may read from <hi>Vers.</hi> 8. to 13. more at large. And <hi>Mark</hi> makes mention of it again, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.3. and <hi>John</hi> likewise, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.1. Now though there is no mention of what she said at that time, yet what she did is recorded; and she is commended by Christ her Lord, as worthy of Commemoration unto all Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, We find <hi>Pilate's</hi> Wife speaking in behalf of Christ, when her Husband was sate down on the Judgment-seat, she sent unto him, saying, <hi>Have thou nothing to do with that just man, for I have suffered many things this day in a Dream because of him,</hi> Mat. 27.19.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, We find the Woman that was twelve Years diseased, and had spent all her Living upon Physitians, and still grew worse and worse; her Faith in Christ was so strong, that she believed, and also said, <hi>If I may touch but the Hem of his Garment, I shall be whole,</hi> Mark 5.25. and so on. And when Christ felt healing Virtue go out of him, he inquired, who it was that touched him? then the Woman came Trembling, and fell down before him, and told him all the truth what she had done: And Christ did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove her for <hi>speaking</hi> to him, but he said unto
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207855:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:207855:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:207855:10"/> her, <hi>Daughter, thy Faith hath made thee whole, go in Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5thly, We find the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> to whom the Angel of God was sent, telling of her, That by the Power of the Most-high, she should bring forth a Son, whose Name should be called <hi>Jesus,</hi> and he should be the Son of the highest, and he should Reign over the House of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom there should be no End, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.26. and so on. Now, though this seemed to her impossible, that such a thing should be, yet in Faith she believed, and said, <hi>Behold the Hand-maid of the Lord, be it unto me accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy Word,</hi> Vers. 38. And then we have her Song of Praise, from <hi>Vers.</hi> 46. to 55. And <hi>Mary</hi> said, <hi>My Soul doth magnifie the Lord, and my Spirit hath rejoyced in God my Saviour; for he hath regarded the low estate of his Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiden: For behold! from hence-forth all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions shall call me Blessed; for he that is mighty hath done to me great things, and Holy is his Name, and his Mercy is unto them that fear him, from Generation to Generation; He hath shewed Strength with his Arm, and hath scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Proud in the Imagination of their Hearts; He hath put down the Mighty from their Seats, and exalted them of low degree; He hath filled the Hungry with good things, and the Rich hath he sent empty away; He hath
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:207855:10"/> holpen his Servant</hi> Israel, <hi>in remembrance of his Mercy, as he spoke to our Fathers, to</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>and his Seed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6thly, We find <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Zacharias</hi> the Priest, saying, <hi>Thus hath the Lord dealt with me, in the day wherein he looked on me, to take away my Reproach among men,</hi> Luke 1.25. This was when she was with-Child of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> the fore-runner of Jesus Christ; and when <hi>Mary</hi> came into her House, she was filled with the Holy Ghost, and spoke out with a loud Voice, saying, <hi>Blessed art thou among Women, and blessed is the Fruit of thy Womb: And whence is this to me, that the Mother of my Lord should come unto me? For lo, as soon as the Voice of thy Salutation sounded in my Ears, the Babe leaped in my Womb for joy: And blessed is she that believed, for there shall be a performance of those things which were told her from the Lord,</hi> Vers. 42. and so on.</p>
            <p n="7">7thly, We find ancient <hi>Anna,</hi> a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess, a Widdow, of about Four-score and four Years of Age, which departed not from the Temple, but served God with Fasting and Prayer, Night and Day; when the Child Jesus was brought thither, she coming in at that instant, gave Thanks unto the Lord, and spake of him to all that looked for Redemption in <hi>Israel, Luk.</hi> 2.36, 37, 38.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:207855:11"/>8thly, We find <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning together, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.39. And when <hi>Martha</hi> would have called her away from sitting at Jesus's Feet, where she heard his Word; Christ reproved her for her cumber, and commended <hi>Mary,</hi> saying, <hi>She hath chosen that good part, which shall not be taken away from her,</hi> Vers. 42. And this is Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicled and left upon Record, that all People might chiefly prefer the better part, and esteem the Word of Truth as the one thing needful.</p>
            <p n="9">9thly, We find certain Women, which followed Christ even to his Crucifixion; see <hi>Mark</hi> 15.40. giving Testimony of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection: <hi>Luke</hi> 24.10. Its said, <hi>It was</hi> Mary Magdalen <hi>and</hi> Joanna, <hi>and</hi> Mary <hi>the Mother of</hi> James, <hi>and other Women that were with them, which told these things unto the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles;</hi> to wit, that Christ was risen. And <hi>Vers.</hi> 22, 23, 24. One of the Brethren, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Cleophas,</hi> confest to Christ, that certain Women of their company made them asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, which were early at the Sepulcher, and when they found not his Body, they came, saying, <hi>That they had seen a Vision of Angels, which said, that he was alive; and certain of them which were with us, went to the Sepulcher, and found it even as the Women had said.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:207855:11"/>10thly, We find Christ, the head of the Church, discoursing with the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> concerning <hi>living Water</hi> &amp; Worship, John 4. from v. 7. to. 27. as you may read at large, <hi>she desired living Water</hi> (v. 15.) and by the Answer Christ gave her, <hi>she perceived him to be a Prophet,</hi> (v. 19.) Then said she to him, <hi>Our Fathers worshipped in this Mountain, and ye say, that in</hi> Jerusalem <hi>is the place where men ought to Worship</hi> (v. 20.) Jesus saith unto her, <hi>Woman, believe me, the hour cometh, when ye shall neither at this Mountain, nor yet at</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem <hi>worship the Father,</hi> (v. 21.) and then he certifieth her, both of the place and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Worship; <hi>But the hour cometh, and NOW IS,</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>when the true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippers shall worship the Father in Spirit and in Truth; for the Father seeketh such to worship him: God is a Spirit, and they that worship him must worship him in Spirit &amp; in Truth</hi> (v. 23, 24.) (This secret Christ revealed to a Woman, and suffered her also to speak freely unto him.) The Woman saith unto him, <hi>I know that</hi> Messias <hi>cometh, which is called Christ, when he is come, he will tell us all things.</hi> Jesus saith unto her, <hi>I that speak unto thee am he,</hi> (v. 25, 26.) And upon this came his Disciples, and marvelled that he talked with the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; but no man said, <hi>Why talkest thou with her?</hi> The Woman then left her Water-pot,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:207855:12"/> and went her way into the City, and said to the men, <hi>Come see a man, which told me all things that ever I did, Is not this the Christ?</hi> v. 28, 29. and many of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> of that City be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in him, for the sayings of the Woman, which testified, <hi>He told me all that ever I did,</hi> v. 39.</p>
            <p n="11">11thly, We find <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> coming early to the Sepulcher on the first day of the Week, &amp; finding the Stone taken away from the Sepulcher, she runneth to <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> and to the other Disciples whom Jesus loved, saying unto them, <hi>They have taken away the Lord out of the Sepulcher, and we know not where they have laid him,</hi> John 20.1, 2. And ver. 11. we find her standing without at the Sepulcher weeping, and as she wept, she stooped down and looketh into the Sepulcher, and seeth two Angels, which said unto her, <hi>Woman, why weepest thou?</hi> she said unto them, <hi>Because they have taken my Lord, and I know not where they have laid him,</hi> v. 13. And when she had thus said, she turned her self back, and saw Jesus standing, but knew not that it was Jesus; Jesus saith unto her, <hi>Woman, why weepest thou; whom seekest thou?</hi> she supposing him to be the Gardner, saith unto him, <hi>Sir, if thou hast born him hence, tell me where thou hast laid him, and I will take him away.</hi> Jesus saith unto her, <hi>Mary;</hi> she turned her self,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207855:12"/> and saith unto him, <hi>Rabboni,</hi> which is to say, <hi>Master;</hi> Jesus saith unto her, <hi>Touch me not, for I am not yet ascended to my Father; but go to my Disciples, and say unto them, I ascend unto my Father and your Father, unto my God and your God: Mary Magdalen</hi> came and told the Disciples this Message, <hi>That she had seen the Lord, and that he had spoken these things unto her;</hi> as you may read from <hi>Vers.</hi> 14. to 18. how Christ conferred with <hi>Mary,</hi> and she with him; unto whom he first shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himself after his Resurrection.</p>
            <p n="12">12thly, We find a certain Woman, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Lydia,</hi> a seller of Purple, of the City of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> which worshipped God, whose Heart the Lord had opened, that she at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto the things that were spoken of <hi>Paul;</hi> and she spake unto him, and them that were with him, saying, <hi>If ye have judged me to be faithful to the Lord, come to my House, and abide there.</hi> So she constrained them, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14, 15. And these her Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, with the Sayings and Doings of many faithful Women more, were Chronicled by the Church for rare Paterns of Love to Christ and his Disciples, to be Examples to their Childrens Children.</p>
            <p n="13">13thly, and <hi>lastly;</hi> As to what I shall now write, we find a certain Damsel possessed with a Spirit of Divination, which brought
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207855:13"/> her Master much Gain by Southsaying; the same followed <hi>Paul,</hi> and other Apostles, and cryed out, saying, <hi>These are the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Most-high God, which shew unto us the Way of Salvation:</hi> And this did she many dayes, <hi>vers.</hi> 17, 18. of the 16th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Acts:</hi> Insomuch that <hi>Paul</hi> was grieved for her, and had compassion on her, so that he turned, and said to the Spirit, <hi>I command thee in the Name of Jesus Christ, to come out of her;</hi> and he came out the same hour. From whence we may take notice, that she obtained the Reward of her Faith, and of her Testimony to the Truth; for as she believed and owned the Apostles to be the Servants of the Lord, so she was dispossessed of the evil Spirit by <hi>Paul,</hi> who spoke in the Name and Power of God.</p>
            <p>Hereunto I might add divers other <hi>instances</hi> of believing Women, as that of <hi>Dorcas,</hi> who is call'd a Disciple of Christ Jesus, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.36. And likewise of <hi>Pricella,</hi> who together with her Husband <hi>Aquilla,</hi> took <hi>Paul</hi> home to their House, when he was first instructed in <hi>Christianity,</hi> and expounded unto him the way of God more perfectly, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.25, 26. And afterwards were Fellow-helpers with <hi>Paul</hi> in Christ Jesus; as himself saith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.3.</p>
            <p>And I might bring in <hi>Philip's</hi> four Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:207855:13"/> which were Prophetesses, sent forth to encourage others.</p>
            <p>And also <hi>Febee,</hi> a woman in esteem in the Church of Christ, whom <hi>Paul</hi> commends and calls, <hi>Their Sister, and a Servant of the Church which is at</hi> Cenchrea, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.1.</p>
            <p>And that Woman, to whom <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelist</hi> sends his Epistle, ought not to be forgot, to wit, <hi>The Elect Lady and her Children, whom I love in the Truth,</hi> saith <hi>John,</hi> 2 Epist. v. 1. But I remember I spoke of Brevity in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, therefore I do but mention these Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies in the latter end, because I find nothing said by them; thus I leave them, designing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to write out of Scripture the Sayings of the Women, and not to say much of them.</p>
            <p>So I shall draw to a <hi>Conclusion,</hi> laying down this assertion, viz. That as Male and Female are made one in Christ Jesus, so Women re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an Office in the Truth as well as Men, and they have a Stewardship, &amp; must give an account of their Stewardship to their Lord, as well as the Men: Therefore they ought to be faithful to God, and valiant for his Truth upon the Earth, that so they may receive the reward of Righteousness, which is as they are faithful to their little, so shall they be made rulers over much: And as they patiently continue in well-doing, seeking Glory, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Virtue, so shall they obtain a Crown of Immortality and Eternal Life, when they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207855:14"/> shall have passed through this Vale of Trouble and Tears; then shall that blessed Sentance be finally pronounced on them, <hi>Well done good and faithful Servants, enter into the undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbed Rest and Joy of your Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Elizabeth Bathurst.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>ALthough the <hi>Woman</hi> was first in the Transgression, which brought in Death; yet was she made by the Power of the Lord, to bring in him <hi>who is the Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Life:</hi> For this was the Promise of the Father, <hi>That the Seed of the Woman should bruise the Serpents Head,</hi> Gen. 3.15. And it is long since fulfilled: For in the fulness of time Christ came, being born of a <hi>Woman,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> as 'tis written, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.23. So that it may be said, <hi>As by Woman came in the Transgression and Degeneration; So by Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man also came in the Reconciliation and Restora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to wit, <hi>Christ,</hi> who came of the Woman's Seed; <hi>He it is, who is the Healer of our Breaches, and Restorer of our Paths; And in him Male and Female are made all one,</hi> as saith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:207855:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>